<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-MUR23841-MY6-TK-GKY"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S1888 IS: Advanced Aviation Integration Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 1888</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230608">June 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S357">Mrs. Fischer</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S386">Ms. Duckworth</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSCM00">Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To provide for the safe and timely integration of advanced aviation technologies into the national airspace system by the Federal Aviation Administration and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="H82C4B8B0A7C540AC8A7AF0D2FC08EE74" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advanced Aviation Integration Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7C1AC6981DF74D42872B7EFC8B58B7DA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Advanced Aviation Leadership</header><subsection id="H443AD156E2E849468D0582AA2E5739E9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall designate the Deputy Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration as the executive responsible for leadership, coordination, and integration of advanced aviation in the national airspace system.</text></subsection><subsection id="H461AE723FFC2496C88AC08796615CDF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The responsibilities of the Deputy Administrator (including any designee of the Deputy Administrator) shall include the following: </text><paragraph id="id149cce0c40d247eb899c5eeaea44e957"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Coordinate across relevant offices of the Administration to facilitate the necessary planning for policy, rulemaking, and approval processes on matters relating to the safe operation and integration of advanced aviation systems in the national airspace system. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id30e627f77d204a9592b48ad512cfa689"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Coordinate across relevant offices of the Administration on the development, assessment, and refinement of advanced aviation systems concepts to ensure feasibility and viability within the national airspace system, including coordination of research and conducting studies and demonstrations to prove concepts. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H282D6E0A03A144BD8C002BC59812EF3D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinate workforce planning across relevant offices of the Administration to—</text><subparagraph id="H60EDBC44957F409D86CC60642CEDD0B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>hire and recruit personnel to—</text><clause id="HD30B17A9BE6B489F8E23C3FF2BDF8C18"><enum>(i)</enum><text>research, develop, test, and evaluate advanced aviation systems; and</text></clause><clause id="H7DBF1330664249E48106D14AC5F9B071"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>process hiring applications related to advanced aviation systems in a timely manner; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BE9FC0892B64FBCA51690C8AA36D25E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop and submit a biannual report to the Secretary and the Administrator, including—</text><clause id="HEAA7B8D0524C47B6A1449E25BFA33A24"><enum>(i)</enum><text>core workforce requirements related to the research, development, testing, and evaluation of advanced aviation systems by the Administration;</text></clause><clause id="H12F6F3344C76471AB0E7AD039F76102B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>core workforce requirements related to the safety, certification, and operational approval of advanced aviation systems by the Administration; and</text></clause><clause id="HA5EFC22F1D0A47A0B9A4F6FAE37B7C15"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>recommendations on staffing and budgetary resources needed to address areas of concern.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AFCA3CCEBBD459EA8D191A0AD2988F1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinate across relevant offices of the Administration to facilitate the United States leadership and participation in activities relating to the international standardization of airworthiness and the operational and environmental effects of advanced aviation systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E7B0C662E8E49F389EA90A40845559B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Advise the Administrator during internal and interagency coordination on advanced aviation systems and other matters.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H095CCADD1A5D417FA34A8F3BFFED5B38"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Advise the Chief Operating Officer of the Administration on the development of enterprise architecture.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EACAB6464614FC2800EF44916652A10"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Validate supporting system requirements proposed by the Chief Operating Officer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57F694BA7E1340F29FE4F244B22468EF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Participate in aviation rulemaking committees related to advanced aviation systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc108c9db31784d028107f95df35fb371"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Serve as the new Designated Federal Official for the Advanced Aviation Advisory Committee and consult with and assign tasks to the Advanced Aviation Advisory Committee.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DA024697D8F41A887150920E1504795"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Use the Administration's clearinghouse website for publicly available data (commonly referred to as <quote>Data.FAA.gov</quote>) to ensure the establishment and implementation of a secure, single-sign on for all FAA-related services (including pending certifications, applications, IACRA, CAPS, DroneZone, MedXpress, CARES, and any other service deemed appropriate by the Administration) with multifactor authentication-protected online capability that allows stakeholders with a new or pending certification or approval application to review the status of such application, receive notice of deadlines and major certification milestones, identify the Administration office that is reviewing such application, and submit inquiries or requests for guidance pursuant to subsection (c).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA282F8741014BB8AED290877F80FEAB"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Work with relevant offices of the Administration to develop and implement pilot programs in partnership with advanced aviation stakeholders to provide data to support rulemaking and approval processes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12ACD5FDE03E4FDFBC0599F38AC28EE5"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Serve as a representative of the Administration during interagency coordination of policies related to advanced aviation systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id97265ba39a934593b70465fd55e16a22"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Provide an opportunity for stakeholders to submit requests or inquiries related to advanced aviation systems to the Office of Advanced Aviation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B960307ADC8436CBE8D9CABDC25F95C"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Promote the safe and responsible integration of advanced aviation systems into the national airspace system.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9E01728BC0404C839D1FEF5F822E5C77" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Request for guidance on operational approval applications</header><text>Any person who submits an operational approval application may include a request for the Assistant Administrator for Advanced Aviation to provide guidance on the processing and coordination required for such request.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3DCE06170C6C41E681F83DCAF596D973"><enum>3.</enum><header>Office of Advanced Integration</header><subsection id="H5F256DD5FB564C12A7EB938F62CDC91B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Deputy Administrator shall redesignate the National Airspace System Engineering and Integration Office as the Office of Advanced Integration within the Office of Advanced Aviation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H799379ED267E4DA8948416C47E242C79"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Deputy Administrator, in consultation with the Administrator and Secretary, shall appoint a Director of Advanced Integration to head the Office of Advanced Integration.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCDDA87AA4E96415C9EB7565C60D161C2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Deputy Administrator shall delegate to the Director of Advanced Integration the responsibilities described in paragraphs (1) through (4) of section 2(b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HB7C20267661D41259B1C2A6E09EC030E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of Advanced Integration shall collaborate with the following:</text><paragraph id="HBC9A30F65E1F4BAE84A646522A3F5C2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Vice President of Air Traffic Services of the Administration and the Vice President of Mission Support Services of the Administration to carry out the responsibilities described in section 2(b)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AF78459CC184E719599D7E4051C4BA1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Executive Director of Aircraft Certification Service of the Administration, the Executive Director of Flight Standards Services of the Administration, and the Executive Director of the Office of Rulemaking of the Administration to carry out the responsibilities described in paragraphs (1) and (3) of section 2(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DF95A8418DA460EB1F19660126F1FF9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the William J. Hughes Technical Center of the Administration to carry out the responsibilities described in section 2(b)(3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4682EACC832747C29D3FD4D7966139A8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Administrator for Finance and Management of the Administration and the Assistant Administrator for Human Resource Management of the Administration to carry out the responsibilities described in section 2(b)(4).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC495129DB794499DA79CFC5ED1AFC261"><enum>4.</enum><header>Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit</header><subsection id="HD8E3EBC7253A467C9BD9D2D17A1911AE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a coordination unit within the Administration to carry out the responsibilities described in subsection (d), to be known as the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit.</text></subsection><subsection id="H268208DC95874DBC8D55C644F92FE718"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit shall consist of the head of each relevant office of the Administration, or an employee representing such office, including—</text><paragraph id="H54B5A065578A46559CC39A4D2A6E8B9C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Office of Advanced Integration established under section 3;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H268502E533774D139EE786EDFFC80A02"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Office of Aviation Safety, including the UAS Integration Office, the Aircraft Certification Service, the Flight Standards Service, and the Office of Rulemaking;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE295EF0F3DD946898BEDE9D1F44ECDB7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Air Traffic Organization, including the Program Management Organization, the Technical Operations Services, the Office of Mission Support Services, and the office headed by the Chief Operating Officer;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ideb24d7134c8d4e4b99aca790e51ba444"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Office of Security and Hazardous Materials Safety;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4123250d717a45a7a971e37732856801"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Office of Airports; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H107924CDC627468CB2221AD14CC32AA5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Office of the Chief Counsel;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71AA56F734AB4BE2B90D45CA5C6F438B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Office of Policy, International Affairs, and Environment; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1c50297efb514be9b2a3c7676ea5a72e"><enum>(8)</enum><text>any other office determined appropriate by the Deputy Administrator.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H24819878A4BF4D128D996C8B5CB013ED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Chair</header><paragraph id="H3BA68BC1B80447F4AE4F56525C281A6A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of Advanced Integration shall serve as the Chair of the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit, at the discretion of the Deputy Administrator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2DEAFC93C204B86B12648BC75D75482"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The Chair may—</text><subparagraph id="H55789D3F250544BAB13FF60AAD37F3FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>schedule meetings of the members of the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62A4CD530C7B4C50B5F459B2AA2CC2E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify items for the members of the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit to act on in fulfillment of the responsibilities described in subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD96D13D56AC42EBA16D36A1B76D7E65"><enum>(C)</enum><text>establish working groups in addition to the working groups established pursuant to subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2A5BE434B74A4EB6862EBAE58ED639CC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The members of the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit shall collaborate to—</text><paragraph id="H3F4AC66F72E848B1B314C26C0EA2E3E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote the safe and responsible integration of advanced aviation systems into the national airspace system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EF9B590E60245CEB4A47B5010CE7EDA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>improve processes related to such integration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H108B8065294541CCB5AB2907D4A1FB0F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>improve processes related to the certification of advanced aviation systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B57F188432945178EDE3C30F36C3CC0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop clear and consistent standards related to advanced aviation systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70A92E6A7F2F431BB50B05B8024BCF1F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ensure that determinations of the Administration related to advanced aviation systems are made in a timely manner; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC2C297CC1EF43E78AD27704967DD295"><enum>(6)</enum><text>identify innovative aviation technologies that may be integrated into the national airspace system.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd3ed88f4d98a4e30a893f6d720de4e5f"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Working groups</header><paragraph id="ida83dad2069d34dc38f8191739862ab85"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Chair of the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit shall establish within the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit a working group on each of the following topics:</text><subparagraph id="id9173e4fbbba042829f0f1a52f87779a4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Unmanned aircraft system integration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbf778a5c659f421f8a54137847ca8997"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Advanced air mobility integration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idabe37b71e72248c5a3881ea35832dac7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Safety technology integration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idfc9e649f2ae84a5991252eb4bb84017d"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Personnel</header><text>The Chair shall consult with the members of the Advanced Coordination Unit on the assignment of Administration personnel to staff the working groups established under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id48bbf21459a94d6b98b003b4ff84b21a"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Projects</header><text>The Chair shall, in consultation with the Administrator and members of the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit, assign projects to the working groups established under paragraph (1) and oversee the execution of such projects.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6d09d0b753a84fbe95b888ab88da1dbd"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Deputy Administrator shall consult with the Administrator and members of the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit to ensure that existing projects of the Administration are incorporated into the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit in a minimally disruptive manner. </text></subsection><subsection id="H43868839CE7E4D1BBC678EEABC28F876"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Interagency coordination</header><text>The Secretary may facilitate coordination between interagency partners and the members of the Advanced Aviation Coordination Unit to fulfill the responsibilities described in subsection (d).</text></subsection></section><section id="HD881343F257B4D0C8996CD0703777A94"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HD1007FB9CBAD4B9E8CDCCD261AB902CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A29C0F4BEEF4CFEAACCA51EDB3E58B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The term <term>Administration</term> means the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H383D7CDDAFB94450BE3CA4C39F910AD7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Advanced aviation system</header><text>The term <term>advanced aviation system</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HBC68C6AD4E6A43BDB711EC7803A8CFBC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an unmanned aircraft system;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA606F8E82C74F19A7219977C001FD82"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a powered lift aircraft;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72685FD808D1405FBA348B36B35D548F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a technology related to—</text><clause id="H188B54EB608F43B393D75D27794B0359"><enum>(i)</enum><text>advanced air mobility; </text></clause><clause id="H86DCA4B99D144C1BA580C320341A9430"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the ability of an aircraft to detect surroundings and avoid impacts;</text></clause><clause id="H3C7647C6316443CD8E75FC388894AED8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">autonomous functioning of aircraft;</text></clause><clause id="H016806DE89A94FE69AB8818243240442"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>supersonic aircraft capabilities;</text></clause><clause id="H5E8F21DD37114505B6C1FEF0217912E8"><enum>(v)</enum><text>electric or hydrogen based aircraft propulsion; or</text></clause><clause id="H8167D80AA40B4C32B4D6BCD169B097BD"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>evolving aerospace operations including new aircraft, airport, weather, or info-centric and digital systems; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61C9846069F04CC9980225FAF1414209"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other aviation-related technology that the Deputy Administrator determines qualifies as an advanced aviation system that could feasibly be integrated into the national airspace system.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idc5b1998410a140208f5e70bbaf8fa7c1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Operational approval application</header><text>The term <term>operational approval application</term> means an application for the operation of an advanced aviation system in the national airspace system submitted pursuant to section 44701 or 44807 of title 49, United States Code, or any other provision of law related to such operation. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DDC8B4CABC44397B2B40606AF916F9C" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

